Let me ask you all a question.
دعوني أطرح عليكم سؤالاً.
How much weapons-grade nuclear material do you think it would take
في اعتقادكم، كم من الأسلحة النووية نحتاج
to level a city the size of San Francisco?
لتدمير مدينة بحجم سان فرانسيسكو؟
How many of you think it would be an amount
كم منكم يعتقد أنها ستكون
about the size of this suitcase?
تقريباً بحجم هذه الحقيبة؟
OK. And how about this minibus?
حسناً، ماذا عن هذه الحافلة الصغيرة؟
All right.
حسناً.
Well actually, under the right circumstances,
في الحقيقة، وتحت الظروف الصحيحة
an amount of highly enriched uranium about the size of your morning latte
كمية من اليورانيوم عالي التخصيب تقريباً بحجم كوب من القهوة
would be enough to kill 100,000 people
سيكون كافياً لقتل 100,000
instantly.
فوراً.
Hundreds of thousands of others would become horribly ill,
مئات الآلاف من الآخرين سوف يمرضون على نحوٍ مُخيف،
and parts of the city would be uninhabitable for years,
و أجزاء من المدينة سوف تكون غير قابله للسكن لسنوات،
if not for decades.
إن لم يكن لعقود.
But you can forget that nuclear latte,
انسوا أمر هذه الكمية الصغيرة من النووي،
because today's nuclear weapons are hundreds of times more powerful
لأن اليوم، الأسلحة النووية أقوى مئات المرات
even than those we dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
حتى من تلك التي اُلقيت علي هيروشيما وناغازاكي.
And even a limited nuclear war involving, say, tens of nuclear weapons,
وحتى حرب نووية محدودة تشمل، مثلاً، عشرات من الأسلحة النووية،
could lead to the end of all life on the planet.
يمكن أن تؤدي إلى نهاية الحياة على هذا الكوكب
So it's really important that you know
لهذا، يجب عليك أن تعرف
that right now we have over 15,000 nuclear weapons
في الوقت الحالي، لدينا ما يزيد عن 15.000 سلاح نووي
in the hands of nine nations.
في أيدي تسع دول.
And if you live in a city or near a military facility,
و لو كنت تعيش في مدينة أو بالقرب من منشأة عسكرية
one is likely pointed right at you.
من المرجح أن أحد هذه الأسلحة موجه إليك.
In fact, if you live in any of the rural areas
في الحقيقة، إن كنت تعيش في منطقة نائية
where nuclear weapons are stored globally,
حيث يتم تخزين الأسلحة النووية في العالم،
one is likely pointed at you.
من المحتمل أن إحداها موجه إليك.
About 1,800 of these weapons are on high alert,
حوالي 1,800 من هذه الأسلحة في حالة تأهب قصوى،
which means they can be launched within 15 minutes
ما يعني أنها يمكن أن تُطلق خلال 15 دقيقة
of a presidential command.
بعد أمر رئاسي.
So I know this is a bummer of an issue,
لذلك، هذه هي المشكلة في القضية،
and maybe you have that -- what was it? -- psychic fatigue
وربما يكون لديك ذلك -- ماذا كان؟ -- التعب النفسي
that we heard about a little bit earlier.
الذي سمعنا عنه سابقاً.
So I'm going to switch gears for just a second,
سأقوم بتغيير الموضوع لثانية،
and I'm going to talk about my imaginary friend,
وسوف أتحدث عن صديقتي الخيالية،
who I like to think of as Jasmine,
التي أحب أن أناديها (ياسمين)،
just for a moment.
لدقيقة فقط.
Jasmine, at the age of 25,
(ياسمين) بعمر 25 سنة،
is part of a generation that is more politically and socially engaged
هي جزء من مجمتع مرتبط بالسياسة والمجتمع
than anything we've seen in 50 years.
أكثر من أي شيء رأيناه في 50 عاماً.
She and her friends think of themselves
هي وصديقاتها يعتبرون أنفسهم
as change agents and leaders and activists.
كعناصر تغيير وقادة ونشطاء.
I think of them as Generation Possible.
و أنا أفكر فيهم بأنهم جيل "الممكن."
They regularly protest about the issues they care about,
وهم يحتجون بانتظام حول القضايا التي تهمهم،
but nuclear weapons are not one of them, which makes sense,
و لكن الأسلحة النووية ليست أحدها، وهو أمر منطقي،
because Jasmine was born in 1991, at the end of the Cold War.
لأن (ياسمين) من مواليد العام 1991، في نهاية الحرب الباردة.
So she didn't grow up hearing a lot about nuclear weapons.
لذا لم تنشأ وهي تسمع كثيراً عن القنابل النووية.
She never had to duck and cover under her desk at school.
و لم تضطر إلى الاختباء والاحتماء تحت مقعدها في المدرسة.
For Jasmine, a fallout shelter is an app in the Android store.
بالنسبة لياسمين، "ملجأ الطوارئ" هو تطبيق في متجر أندرويد.
Nuclear weapons help win games.
الأسلحة النووية تساعدها على الفوز في الألعاب.
And that is really a shame,
و هذا أمر مؤسف حقاً.
because right now, we need Generation Possible
لأننا الآن بحاجة إلى جيل "الممكن"
to help us make some really important decisions about nuclear weapons.
لمساعدتنا في اتخاذ قرارات مصيرية بشأن الأسلحة النووية
For instance, will we further reduce our nuclear arsenals globally,
على سبيل المثال، سوف نقلل الترسانات النووية في العالم،
or will we spend billions,
أو ننفق ملايين،
maybe a trillion dollars,
أو ربما بلايين الدولارات،
to modernize them so they last throughout the 21st century,
لتحديثها لتستمر في القرن الواحد وعشرون،
so that by the time Jasmine is my age, she's talking to her children
و عندما تكون (ياسمين) بعمري، ستتحدث لأطفالها
and maybe even her grandchildren
أو ربما لأحفادها
about the threat of nuclear holocaust?
حول تهديد المحرقة النووية؟
And if you're paying any attention at all to cyberthreats,
و إذا ما كنت تولي اهتماماً للتهديدات الإلكترونية،
or, for instance, if you've read about the Stuxnet virus
أو على سبيل المثال إذا ما قرأت عن فيروس "ستكسنت"
or, for God's sake, if you've ever had an email account or a Yahoo account
أو إذا كان لديك حساب بريد إلكتروني أو حساب "ياهو"
or a phone hacked,
أو حتى هاتف جوال تم إختراقه،
you can imagine the whole new world of hurt that could be triggered
يمكنك أن تتخيل العالم الجديد من المعاناة التي يمكن أن تتولد
by modernization in a period of cyberwarfare.
بواسطة التحديث في فترة الحرب الإلكترونية.
Now, if you're paying attention to the money,
الآن، إن كنت تولي اهتماماً للمال،
a trillion dollars could go a long way
تريليون دولار يمكن أن تقطع شوطاً طويلاً
to feeding and educating and employing people,
في تغذية وتعليم وتوظيف الناس،
all of which could reduce the threat of nuclear war to begin with.
والتي يمكن أن تقلل من خطر الحرب النووية في أن تبدأ بسببها.
So --
وبالتالي --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is really crucial right now,
هذا حقاً أمر بالغ الأهمية الآن،
because nuclear weapons -- they're vulnerable.
لأن الأسلحة النووية -- مُعرضة للخطر.
We have solid evidence
لدينا أدلة دامغة
that terrorists are trying to get ahold of them.
على أن الإرهابيين يحاولون إمتلاك هذه الأسلحة.
Just this last spring,
في الربيع الماضي،
when four retirees and two taxi drivers were arrested
عندما ألقي القبض على أربعة متقاعدين و اثنين من سائقي الأجرة،
in the Republic of Georgia
في جمهورية جورجيا
for trying to sell nuclear materials for 200 million dollars,
لمحاولتهم بيع مواد نووية بقيمة 200 مليون دولار،
they demonstrated that the black market for this stuff is alive and well.
و أظهرو أن هذه الاشياء مطلوبة بكثرة في السوق السوداء.
And it's really important,
و من المهم حقاً،
because there have been dozens of accidents
لأن هناك العشرات من الحوادث
involving nuclear weapons,
تورطت فيها أسلحة نووية،
and I bet most of us have never heard anything about them.
و أراهن على أن مُعظمنا لم يسمعوا شيئاً عنها.
Just here in the United States,
فقط هنا في الولايات المتحدة،
we've dropped nuclear weapons on the Carolinas twice.
ألقينا أسلحة نووية في كارولينا مرتين.
In one case, one of the bombs,
في إحدى الحالتين، واحدة من القنابل،
which fell out of an Air Force plane,
التي اُلقيت من طائرة سلاح الجو،
didn't detonate
لم تنفجر
because the nuclear core was stored somewhere else on the plane.
لأن القلب النووي تم تخزينه في مكان آخر على متن الطائرة.
In another case, the weapon did arm when it hit the ground,
في الحالة الأخرى، القنبلة انفجرت بمجرد ملامستها الأرض،
and five of the switches designed to keep it from detonating failed.
و المفاتيح الخمسة التي تم تصميميها لمنعها من الانفجار، فشلت
Luckily, the sixth one didn't.
و لحسن الحظ، لم يفشل السادس.
But if that's not enough to get your attention,
و إذا لم يكن هذا كافياً للفت انتباهكم،
there was the 1995 Black Brant incident.
كانت هناك حادثة "بلاك برانت" في عام 1995.
That's when Russian radar technicians saw
عندما اكتشف فني رادار روسي
what they thought was a US nuclear missile
ما اعتقدوا أنه صاروخ نووي للولايات المتحدة
streaking towards Russian airspace.
موجه نحو المجال الجوي الروسي.
It later turned out to be a Norwegian rocket
و تبين فيما بعد أنه صاروخ نرويجي
collecting data about the northern lights.
يجمع المعلومات عن الأضواء الشمالية.
But at that time,
و لكن في ذلك الوقت،
Russian President Boris Yeltsin came within five minutes
تراجع الرئيس الروسي (بوريس يلتسين) قبل خمس دقائق
of launching a full-scale retaliatory nuclear attack
من شن هجوم نووي انتقامي
against the United States.
على الولايات المتحدة.
So, most of the world's nuclear nations
لذلك، فإن معظم الدول النووية في العالم
have committed to getting rid of these weapons of mass destruction.
تعاهدت على التخلص من أسلحة الدمار الشامل.
But consider this:
ولكن خذ في عين الاعتبار:
the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons,
معاهدة عدم انتشار الأسلحة النووية،
which is the most widely adopted arms control treaty in history
والتي اعتمدت على نطاق واسع كأكبر معاهدة للحد من الأسلحة في التاريخ
with 190 signatories,
مع 190 توقيع،
sets no specific date by which the world's nuclear-armed nations
لم تحدد موعداً محدداً للدول المسلحة نووياً في العالم
will get rid of their nuclear weapons.
للتخلص من أسلحتها النووية.
Now, when John F. Kennedy sent a man to the moon
الآن، عندما أرسل (جون ف. كينيدي) الإنسان إلى القمر
and decided to bring him back, or decided to do both those things,
و قرر إعادته، أو قرر الاثنين معاً،
he didn't say, "Hey, whenever you guys get to it."
لم يقل، "يا رجال عندما تصلون إلى هناك."
He gave us a deadline.
بل قام بتحديد موعد نهائي.
He gave us a challenge
منحنا تحدياً
that would have been incredible just a few years earlier.
كان غير قابل للتصديق في بضع سنوات سابقة.
And with that challenge,
و مع هذا التحدي،
he inspired scientists and marketers,
ألهم علماء ومسوّقين،
astronauts and schoolteachers.
علماء فضاء وأساتذة.
He gave us a vision.
ومنحنا رؤية.
But along with that vision,
و لكن مع طول الرؤية،
he also tried to give us -- and most people don't know this, either --
حاول أن يعطينا شيئاً أيضاً، معظم الناس لم ينتبهوا له --
he tried to give us a partner
حاول أن يقدم لنا شريكاً
in the form of our fiercest Cold War rival, the Soviet Union.
في شكل منافسنا الأشرس أيام الحرب الباردة، الاتحاد السوفيتي.
Because part of Kennedy's vision for the Apollo program
لأن جزءاً من رؤية (كينيدي) لبرنامج أبولو
was that it be a cooperation, not a competition, with the Soviets.
كان من المفترض أن يكون تعاوناً وليس منافسةً مع السوفيات.
And apparently, Nikita Khrushchev, the Soviet Premier, agreed.
وعلى ما يبدو، وافق عليه رئيس الوزراء السوفياتي (نيكيتا خروتشوف).
But before that cooperation could be realized,
لكن قبل أن يتحقق ذلك التعاون،
Kennedy was assassinated,
اغتيل (كينيدي)،
and that part of the vision was deferred.
و تقرر تأجيل ذلك الجزء من الرؤية.
But the promise of joint innovation between these two nuclear superpowers
لكن وعد الابتكار المشترك بين هاتين القوتين النوويتين
wasn't totally extinguished.
لم يخمد تماماً.
Because in 1991, which is the year that Jasmine was born
لأنه في عام 1991، وهو العام الذي ولدت فيه (ياسمين)
and the Soviet Union fell,
وسقط فيه الاتحاد السوفياتي،
these two nations engaged in a project
اشتركت هاتين الدولتين في مشروع
that genuinely does seem incredible today
و الذي حقاً لا يصدق في وقتنا الحالي
in the truest sense of that word,
بالمعنى الحقيقي للكلمة،
which is that the US sent cash to the Russians when they needed it most,
وهو أن الولايات المتحدة أرسلت نقوداً للروس عندما احتاجوا ليها،
to secure loose nuclear materials
لتأمين المواد النووية السائبة
and to employ out-of-work nuclear scientists.
وتوظيف العلماء النوويين العاطلين عن العمل.
They worked alongside American scientists to convert weapons-grade uranium
عملوا جنباً إلى جنب مع العلماء الأميركيين لتحويل يورانيوم الأسلحة النووية
into the type of fuel that can be used for nuclear power instead.
إلى نوع من أنواع الوقود التي يمكن استخدامها للطاقة النووية بدلاً عن ذلك.
They called it, "Megatons to Megawatts."
وسمّوه، "ميجاطن إلى ميجاواط".
So the result is that for over 20 years,
بالتالي كانت النتيجة أنه لأكثر من 20 عاماً،
our two nations had a program
كان لهاتين الدولتين برنامج
that meant that one in 10 lightbulbs in the United States
يعني أن واحداً من 10 مصابيح في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
was essentially fueled by former Russian warheads.
تمت تغذيتها بالكامل من الرؤوس الحربية الروسية السابقة.
So, together these two nations did something truly audacious.
لذلك، فعلت هاتين الدولتين شيئاً جريئاً حقاً معاً.
But the good news is, the global community has the chance
لكن الخبر السار هو، أن المجتمع الدولي لديه فرصة
to do something just as audacious today.
لكي يقوم بشىء جريء مماثل اليوم.
To get rid of nuclear weapons
للتخلص من الأسلحة النووية
and to end the supply of the materials required to produce them,
والحد من توزيع المواد اللازمة لإنتاجها،
some experts tell me would take 30 years.
يقول بعض الخبراء أن ذلك سيستغرق 30 عاماً.
It would take a renaissance of sorts,
الأمر يستحق نهضةً من نوع ما،
the kinds of innovation that, for better or worse,
هذا النوع من الابتكارات التي تستخدم، إما للأفضل أو للأسوء،
underpinned both the Manhattan Project, which gave rise to nuclear weapons,
و دعم كل من مشروع مانهاتن، الذي أدى إلى ظهور الأسلحة النووية،
and the Megatons to Megawatts program.
و مشروع "ميغاطن إلى ميغاواط".
It would take design constraints.
ستكون هناك حاجة إلى قيود التصنيع.
These are fundamental to creativity,
و هي الحاجة الأساسية للإبداع،
things like a platform for international collaboration;
مثل منصة للتعاون الدولي،
a date certain, which is a forcing mechanism;
مُهلة محددة، وهي آلية التزام،
and a positive vision that inspires action.
ورؤية إيجابية تبعث على العمل.
It would take us to 2045.
هذا الأمر سيتحقق بحلول عام 2045.
Now, 2045 happens to be the 100th anniversary
في الواقع، 2045 سيصادف الذكرى المئوية
of the birth of nuclear weapons in the New Mexico desert.
لظهور الأسلحة النووية في صحراء نيو-مكسيكو.
But it's also an important date for another reason.
لكنه أيضاً تاريخ هام لسبب آخر.
It's predicted to be the advent of the singularity,
من المتوقع أن يكون مجيء التفرد،
a new moment in human development,
لحظة جديدة في التنمية البشرية،
where the lines between artificial intelligence and human intelligence blur,
حيث تختفي الخطوط بين الذكاء الصناعي والذكاء البشري،
where computing and consciousness become almost indistinguishable
حيث يصبح من الصعب التمييز بين الحوسبة والوعي،
and advanced technologies help us solve the 21st century's greatest problems:
وأن تساعدنا التقنيات المتقدمة على حل أعظم مشاكل القرن الحادي والعشرين:
hunger, energy, poverty,
الجوع والطاقة والفقر
ushering in an era of abundance.
والدخول في عصر الوفرة.
And we all get to go to space
ونذهب جميعنا إلى الفضاء
on our way to becoming a multi-planetary species.
في طريقنا لنصبح كائنات متعددة الكواكب.
Now, the people who really believe this vision are the first to say
الآن، الناس الذين يؤمنون حقاً بهذه الرؤية هم أول من يقول
they don't yet know precisely how we're going to get there.
أنهم لا يعرفون تحديداً كيف سنصل إلى هناك.
But the values behind their vision
لكن القيم وراء رؤيتهم
and the willingness to ask "How might we?"
والرغبة في طرح هذا السؤال "كيف يمكننا؟"
have inspired a generation of innovators.
قد ألهمت جيلاً من المبدعين.
They're working backward from the outcomes they want,
إنهم يعملون عكس النتائج التي يريدونها،
using the creative problem-solving methods of collaborative design.
باستخدام أساليب حل المشاكل الإبداعية من التصميم التعاوني.
They're busting through obstacles.
إنهم يخترقون العقبات.
They're redefining what we all consider possible.
ويعيدون تعريف كل ما نعتبره ممكناً.
But here's the thing:
لكن هنا الشيء المهم:
that vision of abundance isn't compatible
هذه النظرة عن الوفرة غير متوافقة
with a world that still relies on a 20th-century nuclear doctrine
مع عالم لا يزال يعتمد على مبدأ للأسلحة النووية وضع في القرن العشرين،
called "mutually assured destruction."
والذي يسمى "ضمان التدمير المشترك."
It has to be about building the foundations for the 22nd century.
يجب أن يكون حول بناء أسس القرن الثاني والعشرين.
It has to be about strategies for mutually assured prosperity
يجب أن يكون حول استراتيجيات ضمان الازدهار المشترك
or, at the very least, mutually assured survival.
أو على أقل تقدير، ضمان البقاء المشترك.
Now, every day, I get to meet people who are real pioneers
كل يوم، ألتقي بأناس أعتبرهم روادً حقيقيين
in the field of nuclear threats.
في مجال التهديدات النووية.
As you can see, many of them are young women,
كما ترون، كثير منهم نساء شابات،
and they're doing fiercely interesting stuff,
ويفعلون أشياءً مثيرة للاهتمام بشراسة،
like Mareena Robinson Snowden here, who is developing new ways,
مثل (مارينا روبنسون سنودن)، التي طوّرت طُرقاً جديدة،
better ways, to detect nuclear warheads,
طُرقاً أفضل، للكشف عن الرؤوس الحربية النووية،
which will help us overcome a critical hurdle
والتي سوف تساعدنا في التغلب على عقبة حاسمة
to international disarmament.
و الوصول إلى نزع سلاح عالمي.
Or Melissa Hanham, who is using satellite imaging
أو (ميليسا هنهام)، التي تستخدم صور الأقمار الصناعية
to make sense of what's going on around far-flung nuclear sites.
لمعرفة ما يجري في المواقع النووية البعيدة.
Or we have Beatrice Fihn in Europe,
أو (بياتريس فين) في أوروبا،
who has been campaigning to make nuclear weapons illegal
التي كانت تُدير حملات لجعل الأسلحة النووية غير قانونية
in international courts of law,
في ساحات القانون الدولية،
and just won a big victory at the UN last week.
وحققت انتصاراً كبيراً في الأمم المتحدة الأسبوع الماضي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And yet,
و مع ذلك،
and yet,
ومع ذلك،
with all of our talk in this culture about moon shots,
على الرغم من حديثنا عن سطح القمر في هذه الثقافة،
too few members of Generation Possible and those of us who mentor them
عدد قليل جداً من أعضاء جيل الممكن، و البعض منّا الذين يرشدونهم
are taking on nuclear weapons.
أصبحوا يركزون على الأسلحة النووية.
It's as if there's a taboo.
كما لو أنه من المحرمات.
But I remember something Kennedy said that has really stuck with me,
لكن أتذكر شيئاً قاله (كينيدي) والذي بقي عالقا عالقاً في رأسي،
and that is something to the effect
وهو شيء في الواقع
that humans can be as big as the solutions
أن البشر يمكن أن يكونوا بقدر الحلول
to all the problems we've created.
لجميع المشاكل التي خلقناها.
No problem of human destiny, he said,
قال: "ليست هناك مشكلة تتعلق بمصير الإنسان،
is beyond human beings.
الأمر أبعد من البشر."
I believe that.
و أنا أؤمن بذلك.
And I bet a lot of you here believe that, too.
و أراهن على أن الكثير منكم هنا، يؤمنون بذلك أيضاً.
And I know Generation Possible believes it.
وأنا أعرف أن جيل الممكن يؤمنون بذلك.
So it's time to commit to a date.
لقد حان الوقت لتحديد موعد.
Let's end the nuclear weapons chapter
دعونا نُنهي فصل الأسلحة النووية
on the 100th anniversary of its inception.
في الذكرى المئوية لتأسيسها.
After all, by 2045, we will have held billions of people hostage
الأهم من كل ذلك، بحلول عام 2045، سنكون قد اتخذنا مليارات البشر رهائن
to the threat of nuclear annihilation.
بسبب خطر الإبادة النووية.
Surely, 100 years will have been enough.
ومن المؤكد أن 100 سنة ستكون كافية.
Surely, a century of economic development
بالتأكيد، قرن من التنمية الاقتصادية
and the development of military strategy
وتطور الاستراتيجية العسكرية
will have given us better ways to manage global conflict.
سيمدنا بطرق أفضل لإدارة الصراع العالمي.
Surely, if ever there was a global moon shot worth supporting,
بالتأكيد، إذا ما كانت هناك خطة على سطح القمر تستحق الدعم،
this is it.
هذه هي.
Now, in the face of real threats --
الآن، في مواجهة التهديدات الحقيقية --
for instance, North Korea's recent nuclear weapons tests,
على سبيل المثال، التجارب النووية الأخيرة لكوريا الشمالية،
which fly in the face of sanctions --
التي تتحدى العقوبات --
reasonable people disagree
عدد مقدر من الناس لا يتفقون
about whether we should maintain some number of nuclear weapons
حول ما إذا كان علينا أن نحتفظ ببعض الأسلحة النووية
to deter aggression.
لردع العدوان.
But the question is: What's the magic number?
لكن السؤال هو: ما هو الرقم السحري؟
Is it a thousand?
هل هو ألف؟
Is it a hundred? Ten?
هل هو مائة؟ عشرة؟
And then we have to ask:
ثم علينا أن نسأل:
Who should be responsible for them?
من يجب أن يكون مسؤولاً عنها؟
I think we can agree, however,
وأعتقد أنه يمكننا أن نتفق،
that having 15,000 of them represents a greater global threat
أن وجود 15,000 منها يمثل تهديداً عالمياً كبيراً
to Jasmine's generation than a promise.
على جيل (ياسمين) أكثر من كونه وعداً.
So it's time we make a promise
لذلك حان الوقت لنقطع وعداً
of a world in which we've broken the stranglehold
للعالم الذي كسرنا قبضته
that nuclear weapons have on our imaginations;
بالأسلحة النووية التي تسيطر على خيالنا،
in which we invest in the creative solutions
نستثمره في إيجاد الحلول الإبداعية
that come from working backward from the future we desperately want,
الناتجة من العمل إلى الوراء من المستقبل الذي نسعى له بشدة،
rather than plodding forward from a present
بدلاً عن المشي بخطوات ثقيلة للأمام عن الحاضر
that brings all of the mental models and biases of the past with it.
الذي يجمع كل النماذج الذهنية والتحيزات عن الماضي معه.
It's time we pledge our resources as leaders across the spectrum
لقد حان الوقت لتوحيد مواردنا كقادة من جميع المجالات
to work on this old problem in new ways,
لمواجهة هذه المشكلة القديمة بطرق جديدة،
to ask, "How might we?"
و نتسائل: "كيف يمكننا؟"
How might we make good on a promise
كيف يمكننا أن نفي بوعدنا
of greater security for Jasmine's generation
المتعلق بمزيد من الأمن لجيل (ياسمين)
in a world beyond nuclear weapons?
في عالم خالِ من الأسلحة النووية؟
I truly hope you will join us.
وآمل حقاً أن تنضموا إلينا.
Thank you.
شكرا ً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)